Guide to the Herbert Scarf papers, 1951-2015 RL.11619
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Herbert Scarf papers
1951-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Scarf, Herbert E.
RL.11619
33 Linear Feet 22 boxes
.684 Megabytes 3 floppy disks with 11 files (one disk unreadable)
Herbert Scarf (1930-2015) was an economist and mathematician, and worked as a professor of economics at Yale University and the Cowles Foundation for Research in Economics. This collection consists of his correspondence, research, and writings, as well as his collaborations and professional affiliations across the fields of economics, mathematics, and operations research. Includes a small group of electronic files; computations and other technical data contained in these files may be available in the form of printouts in the collection's research files. Acquired as part of the Economists' Papers Archive at Duke University.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into these series: Correspondence (including name files); Writings; Research and Notes; Academia; and Personal.
Biographical / Historical
Herbert Eli Scarf (1930-2015) was an American economist and mathematician born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. He died at 85 on November 15, 2015 in Sag Harbor, New York. He earned his undergraduate degree (A.B. Mathematics) at Temple University in 1951 and completed his Ph.D. in Mathematics at Princeton University in 1954. From 1954 to 1957 Scarf worked in the Mathematics and Economics Departments and the RAND Corporation before joining Stanford University as an Assistant Professor of Statistics in 1957. In 1963 Scarf joined the Economics Department at Yale University and the Cowles Foundation for Research in Economics. Scarf remained at Yale for the remainder of his career as the Stanley Resor Professor of Economics (1970-1978) and the Sterling Professor of Economics (1979-2015). Scarf was awarded the Frederick W. Lanchester Prize (1973) and the John von Neumann Theory Prize (1983) by the Institute for Operations Research and the Management Sciences, and served as President of the Econometric Society in 1983.
A primary focus of Scarf's research was the computation of economic equilibrium and fixed points, which serves as the basis for applied general equilibrium models. Scarf also made significant contributions to understanding the stability of general equilibrium, the core of many-person games and its relation to general equilibrium, integer programming, and economic production with indivisibilities. Much of Scarf's work is a precursor to modern computational and simulation approaches to economics. His wife, Maggie Scarf, is the author of several award-winning books on family relationships and marriage.
Chronology
1930 Born in Philadelphia, PA
1951 A.B. Mathematics, Temple University
1953 Married Margaret (Maggie) Klein
1954 Ph.D. Mathematics, Princeton University
1954-1957 RAND Corporation
1957-1962 Assistant Professor of Statistics, Stanford University
1963-1970 Professor of Economics, Yale University
1967-1971 Director, Cowles Foundation for Research in Economics
1970-1978 Stanley Resor Professor of Economics, Yale University
1973 Frederick W. Lanchester Prize
1979-2015 Sterling Professor of Economics
1981-1984 Director, Cowles Foundation for Research in Economics
1983 John von Neumann Theory Prize
1983 President, Econometric Society
2015 Nov. 15 Died in Sag Harbor, NY
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Electronic records have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library reading room. To request access, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these records.
Provenance
The Herbert Scarf Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2017.
Collection Overview
The Herbert Scarf Papers document his career as an economist and mathematician. The collection provides an overview of his professional activities, particularly his research and writings on the computation of economic equilibrium and fixed points, stability of general equilibrium, the core of many-person games and its relation to general equilibrium, integer programming, and problems of production with indivisibilities. Much of Scarf's work serves as the basis for applied general equilibrium models, and as a precursor to modern computational and simulation approaches to economics.
The collection also documents Scarf's collaboration and communications with prominent economists and mathematicians such as Kenneth Arrow, Gerard Debreu, Ralph Gomory, Terje Hansen, Werner Hildenbrand, Tjalling Koopmans, Harold Kuhn, Lloyd Shapley, John Shoven, Martin Shubik, John Whalley, and many others.
Along with his own scholarship and writings, the collection documents Scarf's leadership roles in the American Economic Association, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the Econometric Society, and other organizations; and his departmental roles, committee work, and teaching contributions in the economics, operations research, and applied mathematics programs at Yale University.
Includes a small group of electronic files originally on floppy disks created in the 1980s, which have been migrated to a library server. Computations and other technical data contained in these files may be available in the form of printouts in the collection's research files.
Acquired as part of the Economists' Papers Archive at Duke University.
Cooperative games (Mathematics); Economics -- Study and teaching (Higher); Equilibrium (Economics); Game theory -- Research; Integer programming; Microeconomics; Electronic records; Photographs; Arrow, Kenneth J. (Kenneth Joseph), 1921-2017; Debreu, Gerard; Foley, Duncan K.; Gomory, Ralph E.; Hansen, Terje; Shubik, Martin; Hildenbrand, Werner, 1936-; Koopmans, Tjalling C. (Tjalling Charles), 1910-1985; Kuhn, Harold W. (Harold William), 1925-2014; Mandler, Michael; Mantel, Rolf R.; Shapley, Lloyd S., 1923-; Shoven, John B.; Whalley, John; Yale University. Cowles Foundation for Research in Economics; Yale University -- Faculty; American Economic Association
- Correspondence, 1959-2012; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Contains Scarf's name files on various individuals and general correspondence. Scarf maintained correspondence files for particular individuals of note and his Ph.D. advisees (including copies of dissertations), while collecting other correspondence in General Correspondence folders. This series also contains Scarf's correspondence with various publishers and academic journals. Correspondents of note include Kenneth Arrow, Gerard Debreu, Duncan Foley, Ralph Gomory, Werner Hildenbrand, Tim Kehoe, Tjalling Koopmans, Harold Kuhn, Michael Mandler, Rolf Mantel, Joan Robinson, John Shoven, Martin Shubik, and John Whalley.
  - Andersen, Torben, 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Arrow, Kenneth, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    Includes discussion of terminology used in economic theory and routine correspondence
  - Arrow Festschrift Volume, 1983 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence about a possible contribution to a festschrift volume in honor of Arrow
  - Barany, Imre, 1988-1996 (Box 1)
  - Bender, Judith, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Caplin, Andrew, 1983 (Box 1)
    Includes dissertation
  - Chou, Chien-Fu, 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - Cook, William, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Dang, Chuangyin, 1994-1997; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Debreu, Gerard, 1961-1992; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Dybvig, Phili Hallen, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Eaves, Curtis, 1971-1985 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence on dynamic programming and other routine correspondence
  - Feltenstein, Andrew, 1974-1996; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Fixed Points - material & correspondence pertaining to this, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence on fixed points
  - Foley, Duncan, 1965-1991 (Box 1)
    Includes dissertation and correspondence on asset equilibrium with risk and equilibrium in exchange economies
  - Giannetti da Fonseca, Marcos, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Gomory, Ralph, 1990-1995; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence on the existence of equilibrium with economies of scale and a model of international trade with increasing returns
  - Hemmecke, Raymond, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Hansen, Terje, 1972 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence on algorithms for computing fixed points
  - Hartley, Michael, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Hildenbrand, Werner, 1972-1991 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence on the core of economies and other routine correspondence
  - Ibragimov, Rustan, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Kanaan, Oussama, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Kannan, Ravindran, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - Kaplan, Elliot, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Kehoe, Timothy J., 1986-1997 (Box 1)
    Includes routine correspondence
  - Keynes, J.M., 1990s (Box 1)
    Includes modern copy of a 1938 letter by Keynes to FDR
  - Khachiyan, Leonid, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Koopmans, Tjalling, 1960-1991 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence on computation of equilibrium, optimal growth, and other routine correspondence
  - Koopmans, Tjalling, 1991-1998; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence about Koopmans's life by Truus Koopmans, research for a book by Albert Jolink and Philip Mirowski, and drafts and notes for a biography and memorial tribute
  - Kuhn, Harold, 1968-1988; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence about simplex algorithms and the computation of fixed points
  - Lee, Jonathan, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Lenstra's Algorithm, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence about methods of integer programming
  - Leonard, Robert, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    Includes interview on the history of game theory and general equilibrium
  - Levy, Frank S., 1968-1969; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Lovasz, Laszlo, 1986-1993; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence about computation of fixed points
  - Mandler, Michael, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Mantel, Rolf & Ana, 1964-1974 (Box 2)
  - Markowitz, Harry, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Martirena-Mantel, Ana Maria, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Noguchi, Yukio, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Proschen, Frank, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Reichert, Joshua, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Richter, Donald K., 1968-1972 (Box 2)
  - Rikun, Anatoly D., 1992-1995 (Box 2)
  - Rivlin, Alice, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Robinson, Joan, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence about stationary states of economies
  - Rutherford, Tom, 1988-1992 (Box 2)
  - Samuelson, Paul, 1992 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence about the application of the computation of fixed points to transport problems
  - Serra-Puche, Jaime, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Shallcross, David, 1988-1991 (Box 2)
  - Shoven, John, 1972-1992; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Includes dissertation and correspondence on applied general equilibrium models with taxation
  - Shubik, Martin, 1961-1995; 2 folders (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence about the core and competitive equilibrium as well as routine correspondence
  - Smale, Stephen, 1984 (Box 3)
    Includes brief articles by Smale
  - Thomas, Rekha R., 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Todd, Michael, 1972-1976 (Box 3)
  - Tversky, Amos, 1993-1996 (Box 3)
    Includes routine correspondence about Tversky
  - Wang, Xin, 1991-1996; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Whalley, John E., 1972-1996; 2 folders (Box 3)
    Includes dissertation and correspondence on applied general equilibrium modeling
  - White, Philip, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Yang, Zaifu, 1995-1997 (Box 3)
  - Zamansky, Leo, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Zhao, Jingang, 1991-2000; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Zhou, Lin, 1995 (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1962-1985; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1985-2004; 6 folders (Box 4)
  - American Scientist, 1981-1983 (Box 4)
  - Annals of Economic Theory (Journal), 1989 (Box 4)
  - Cambridge University Press, 2012 (Box 4)
  - Discrete Applied Mathematics (Journal), 1978-1993 (Box 4)
  - Econometrica, 1983-1990 (Box 4)
  - Economic Theory (Journal-Editor), 1990-1995 (Box 4)
  - Games and Economic Behavior, 1988-1992 (Box 4)
  - Journal of Mathematical Economics, 1972-1997 (Box 4)
  - Macmillan Press, Ltd., 1985 (Box 4)
  - Operations Research, 1987-1995 (Box 4)
  - Yale University Press, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
- Conferences and Organizations, 1960-2003; undated; 2
  This series includes files on Scarf's professional activities. These include: conference and workshop presentations; files related to service with professional organizations and research institutes and organizations; and files from advising on award committees.
  - AAAS (American Academy of Arts & Sciences), 1982-1997 (Box 4)
  - AAAS: Koopmans Scholarship, 1986 (Box 4)
  - AEA (American Economic Association), 1992-1995 (Box 4)
  - AEA: Nominating Committee, 1992-1994 (Box 4)
  - AEA: US/USSE Exchange, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1993-1998 (Box 4)
  - AMS-IMS-SIAM, 2003 (Box 4)
    Files related to conference in the mathematical sciences
  - Berlin, 1996 (Box 4)
    Files related to workshop on integer programming
  - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, 1962-1995 (Box 4)
    Files related to fellowship at center
  - COCOA Summer School, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Conference in Honor of Ralph Gomory, undated (Box 4)
    Conference program and presentation transparencies
  - Connecticut Academy of Science and Engineering, 1976-1991 (Box 4)
  - CORS/TIMS/ORSA Joint National Meeting, 1989 (Box 4)
    Materials for conference meetings
  - Daedalus (June 1972 Conference at Princeton) (Box 4)
  - Econometric Society, 1960-1997; 2 folders (Box 4)
    Includes files for society fellowship nominations and correspondence related to serving as president and past-president of the society
  - Ford Foundation, 1967-1969 (Box 4)
    Includes files for proposed international institute sponsored by the foundation
  - General Equilibrium Trade Policy Conference, 1984 (Box 4)
    Files for conference at Columbia University
  - Geometry of Numbers & Discrete Production Sets, 1992-1995; 2 folders (Box 5)
    Includes files for NSF-funded project
  - Geometry of Numbers and Integer Programming, 1989; undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
    Includes files and transparencies for presentations on integer programming
  - Guggenheim Fellowship, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - IBM Contract (with Shallcross), 1991-1992 (Box 5)
    Includes files for joint study conducted by Yale and IBM, coordinated by Scarf and David Shallcross
  - IIASA (International Institute for Applied System Analysis), 1971-1989; 3 folders (Box 5)
    Includes files for conferences hosted by the institute
  - International Symposium on Mathematical Programming, 1997 (Box 5)
  - KTH (Sweden) Meeting and IPCO (Denmark), 1995 (Box 5)
    Includes files related to travel for collaboration between Swedish Royal Institute of Technology and Yale, as well as files for conference on Integer Programming and Combinatorial Optimization (IPCO) in Copenhagen sponsored by the Mathematical Optimization Society
  - Lecture/Seminars/Talks/Workshops/Conferences, 1969-1994; 9 folders (Box 5)
    Includes correspondence and documents related to various presentations and events
  - MSRI (Mathematical Sciences Research Institute), 1985-1987 (Box 5)
    Includes files for visits to institute
  - MSRI: Conference Berkeley, 1997 (Box 5)
    Includes files for conference Scarf did not attend
  - Mathematics of Operations Research, 1999; 2 folders (Box 5)
    Includes files for conference presentation in Lunteren, Netherlands
  - MUG (Model Users Group) International, 1995 (Box 5)
  - NAS (National Academy of Sciences), 1976-1991; 2 folders (Box 5)
    Includes files related to serving as chair of the Economic Sciences section of the academy
  - NAS: Ad Hoc Committee - Cost/Benefit Analysis, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    Includes files for committee service evaluating use of cost/benefits analysis for environmental research
  - NAS: Committee on Human Rights, 1977-1994 (Box 5)
    Includes files related to serving on committee
  - NAS: Elections, 1976-2000 (Box 5)
  - NAS: Expenses, 1979-1994 (Box 5)
  - NAS: Meetings, 1985-1995 (Box 5)
  - NAS: Personal, 1976-1995 (Box 5)
    Includes notes of congratulations for election to academy
  - NAS: Proceedings, 1985-1988 (Box 5)
    Includes files related to serving on editorial board of Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
  - NAS: Section Chairman, 1991-1995 (Box 5)
  - NBER (National Bureau of Economic Research), 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 5)
    Includes files for NBER workshop on applied general equilibrium
  - NSF (National Science Foundation): Budget Cuts, 1979-1981 (Box 5)
    Includes letters to Congress arguing against cuts to NSF funding
  - NSF: Evaluations of Proposals, 1984-1995 (Box 5)
    Includes files for evaluating proposals submitted to the NSF
  - NSF: Grant - Scarf/Shoven, 1985 (Box 6)
    Includes proposal for grant to fund NBER workshops and research on applied general equilibrium
  - NSF: Grant - Geometry of Numbers & Discrete Production Sets, 1988-1992 (Box 6)
  - NSF: Grant - Indivisibilities in Production, 1977-1988; 7 folders (Box 6)
    Includes files for grant-funded research on indivisibilities in production
  - NSF: Miscellaneous, 1981-1990; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - NSF: Monthly Statements, 1985-1988 (Box 6)
  - NSF: Proposal - Integer Programming (declined), 1988 (Box 6)
  - NSF: Proposal - Discrete Production Sets (declined), 1995 (Box 6)
  - Nobel Nominations, 1972-1999 (Box 6)
  - One Hundred Economists - Fixing the Economy, 1992 (Box 6)
    Includes correspondence related to open letter by economists to President George Bush on plans for economic recovery
  - Ricardo Model Presentation, undated (Box 6)
    Includes transparencies for a presentation on a Ricardo model of international trade
  - Russell Sage Foundation, 1987-1996 (Box 6)
    Includes correspondence related to the foundation's visiting scholars program
  - Santa Fe Institute, 1991-1996 (Box 6)
    Includes files for institute workshops on integer programming, computational complexity, and increasing returns
  - Scarf Invitations, 1984-1994 (Box 6)
    Includes accepted and declined invitations to conferences and workshops
  - T.N. Srinivasan Birthday, undated (Box 6)
    Includes presentation slides for conference celebrating Srinivasan's birthday
  - Activity Analysis and Computation of Fixed Points Presentation, undated (Box 7)
    Includes presentation slides
  - Computation of Equilibrium Presentation, 1998; undated (Box 7)
  - Indivisibilities in Production Presentation, undated (Box 7)
    Includes notes and presentation slides
  - Integer Programming Presentation, 2001; undated; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Inventory Lecture, undated (Box 7)
    Includes notes and presentation slides for lecture on inventory problems
  - Presentation Notes, 1986-1987 (Box 7)
    Includes unlabeled notes for lectures
- Research and Notes, 1951-2015; 3
  Includes Scarf's notes and correspondence for research projects, and a portion of his collection of academic writings by others. Research notes include files on Scarf's work on general equilibrium theory, the computation of economic equilibrium and fixed points, his collaboration with Terje Hansen, and methods of integer programming to compute economic equilibrium under certain conditions. Of note is a Rolodex with Scarf's bibliographic citations listing articles he referenced or read as part of his research.
  The Research subseries includes three disks containing electronic files related to Scarf's computational projects. One disk was unreadable.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library reading room. To request access, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these records.
  - Research, 155.5 Megabytes 3 floppy disks (11 files and 1 unreadable disk); Two floppy disks containing 11 files (.arc, .exe, .com, .err; .684 MB); and one unreadable disk.
    This subseries contains documents in various formats related to Scarf's research projects, including his work with Terje Hansen, the core and general equilibrium, and computation of economic equilibrium and fixed points.
    Includes a small group of electronic files originally on floppy disks created in the 1980s, which have been migrated to a library server; computations and other technical data contained in these files may be available in the form of printouts in the collection's research files.
    - Computation of Equilibrium, 1973-1976; 1999-2011; undated; 11 folders (Box 7)
      Includes hand-written notes, copies of computer code, printouts of computer simulation output, and correspondence related to research on the computation of economic equilibrium
    - Computation of Equilibrium, undated (Box 8)
    - Computer Programs, 1960s; 1980-1984 (Box 8)
      Includes copies of computer simulation code
    - Core, 1966 (Box 8)
      Includes printouts of computer simulation output for research on computing the core of an economy
    - Core and Equilibrium, 1965-1966; undated; 2 folders (Box 8)
      Includes hand-written notes and drafts for research on the core of cooperative games and competitive equilibrium
    - Hansen's Basic code, 1967-1975 (Box 8)
      Includes copies of computer simulation code and simulation output related to Scarf's work with Terje Hansen on the computation of equilibrium
    - Increasing Returns and International Trade, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
      Includes hand-written notes, copies of computer simulation output, and materials related to research on increasing returns to scale and trade between countries
    - Integer Programming, 1968-1991; 11 folders (Box 8)
      Includes hand-written notes, copies of computer simulation code, and printouts of computer simulation output related to various research projects on integer programming approaches to the computation of economic equilibrium
    - Integer Programming, 1992-2003; 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Lattice Points, 1978; 1970s-1980s; 4 folders (Box 9)
      Includes hand-written notes and materials for research on optimization in lattice-free polyhedra
    - Misc. Notes, undated (Box 9)
      Includes unlabeled miscellaneous notes
    - Operations Research, 1979 (Box 9)
      Includes hand-written notes on operations research
    - Pure Trade Examples, 1966 (Box 9)
      Includes computer simulation output for examples of pure trade economies
    - Scarf - Production, 1963-1970; 2 folders (Box 9)
      Includes computer simulation output and materials for research on the computation of equilibrium in the presence of indivisibilities in production
    - Reference Index, undated (Box 22)
      Includes rolodex cards containing bibliographic information for sources used in Scarf's research. The rolodex is sorted by three major topics (Fixed Points, General, and Integer) and then alphabetically within topic.
    - MPS/GE Program Disk files, 1987-1988; .340 Megabytes 1 floppy disk with 6 files (.arc, .exe., .err, .com) (Digital-materials RL.11619-SET-0001, Disk RL.11619-FL5-0001)
    - MPS/GE Library Disk files, 1988 July; .344 Megabytes 1 floppy disk with 5 files (.arc) (Digital-materials RL.11619-SET-0001, Disk RL.11619-FL5-0002)
    - IRS/TRADE + New MPS/GE Code files (disk unreadable), 1980s? (Digital-materials RL.11619-SET-0001, Disk RL.11619-FL5-0003)
  - Writings by Others
    Includes select articles and book chapters used in Scarf's research. Unindexed files are not indexed by topic; the other topics -- Fixed points, General, and Integer were assigned by Scarf.
    - Fixed Points: A-D, 1910-1970s; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Fixed Points: D-R, 1950s-1984; 6 folders (Box 10)
    - General: A-Manne, 1952-1985; 7 folders (Box 10)
    - General: Mantel-Y, 1960-1985; 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Integer: Balas, 1992 (Box 11)
    - Integer: Be-Gi, 1974-1977 (Box 11)
    - Integer: Gomory, 1958-1961 (Box 11)
    - Integer: Gomory-H, 1960-1977 (Box 11)
    - Integer: J-W, 1960-1982; 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Unindexed: A-C, 1950s-2000s; 4 folders (Box 11)